<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

         http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->

<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Log4j 2 Appenders</title>
        <author email="rgoers@apache.org">Ralph Goers</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
      <section name="Appenders">
        <p>
          Appenders are responsible for delivering LogEvents to their destination. Every Appender must
          implement the <a href="../log4j-core/apidocs/org/apache/logging/log4j/core/Appender.html">Appender</a>
          interface. Most Appenders will extend
          <a href="../log4j-core/apidocs/org/apache/logging/log4j/core/appender/AbstractAppender.html">AbstractAppender</a>
          which adds <a href="../log4j-core/apidocs/org/apache/logging/log4j/core/Lifecycle.html">Lifecycle</a>
          and <a href="../log4j-core/apidocs/org/apache/logging/log4j/core/filter/Filterable.html">Filterable</a>
          support. Lifecycle allows components to finish initialization after configuration has completed and to
          perform cleanup during shutdown. Filterable allows the component to have Filters attached to it which are
          evaluated during event processing.
        </p>
        <p>
          Appenders usually are only responsible for writing the event data to the target destination. In most cases
          they delegate responsibility for formatting the event to a <a href="../layouts.html">layout</a>. Some
          appenders wrap other appenders so that they can modify the LogEvent, handle a failure in an Appender,
          route the event to a subordinate Appender based on advanced Filter criteria or provide similar functionality
          that does not directly format the event for viewing.
        </p>
        <p>
          Appenders always have a name so that they can be referenced from Loggers.
        </p>
        <a name="AsynchAppender"/>
        <subsection name="AsynchAppender">
          <p>The AsynchAppender accepts references to other Appenders and causes LogEvents to be written to them
            on a separate Thread. Note that exceptions while writing to those Appenders will be hidden from
            the application. The AsynchAppender should be configured after the appenders it references to allow it
            to shut down properly.</p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>appender-ref</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appenders to invoke asynchronously. Multiple appender-ref
                elements can be configured.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>blocking</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>If true, the appender will wait until there are free slots in the queue. If false, the event
                will be written to the error appender if the queue is full.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>bufferSize</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>Specifies the maximum number of events that can be queued. The default is 128.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>error-ref</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender to invoke if none of the appenders can be called, either due to errors
                in the appenders or because the queue is full. If not specified then errors will be ignored.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
                may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">AsynchAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
          <p>
            A typical AsynchAppender configuration might look like:

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <File name="MyFile" fileName="logs/app.log">
      <PatternLayout>
        <pattern>%d %p %C{1.} [%t] %m%n</pattern>
      </PatternLayout>
    </File>
    <Asynch name="Asynch">
      <appender-ref ref="MyFile"/>
    </Asynch>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="Asynch"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <a name="ConsoleAppender"/>
        <subsection name="ConsoleAppender">
          <p>
            As one might expect, the ConsoleAppender writes its output to either System.err or System.out with System.err
            being the default target. A Layout must be provided to format the LogEvent.
          </p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
              may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>layout</td>
              <td>Layout</td>
              <td>The Layout to use to format the LogEvent. If no layout is supplied the default pattern layout
              of "%m%n" will be used.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>follow</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>Identifies whether the appender honors reassignments of System.out or System.err
                via System.setOut or System.setErr made after configuration. Note that the follow
                attribute cannot be used with Jansi on Windows.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>target</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>Either "SYSTEM_OUT" or "SYSTEM_ERR". The default is "SYSTEM_ERR".</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">ConsoleAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
          <p>
            A typical Console configuration might look like:

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <Console name="STDOUT" target="SYSTEM_OUT">
      <PatternLayout pattern="%m%n"/>
    </Console>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="STDOUT"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <a name="FailoverAppender"/>
        <subsection name="FailoverAppender">
          <p>The FailoverAppender wraps a set of appenders. If the primary Appender fails the secondary appenders will be
          tried in order until one succeeds or there are no more secondaries to try.</p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
              may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>primary</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the primary Appender to use.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>failovers</td>
              <td>String[]</td>
              <td>The names of the secondary Appenders to use.</td>
            </tr>

            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>retryInterval</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>The number of seconds that should pass before retrying the primary Appender. The default is 60.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>target</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>Either "SYSTEM_OUT" or "SYSTEM_ERR". The default is "SYSTEM_ERR".</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">FailoverAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
          <p>
            A Failover configuration might look like:

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <RollingFile name="RollingFile" fileName="logs/app.log"
                 filePattern="logs/app-%d{MM-dd-yyyy}.log.gz">
      <PatternLayout>
        <pattern>%d %p %C{1.} [%t] %m%n</pattern>
      </PatternLayout>
      <TimeBasedTriggeringPolicy />
    </RollingFile>
    <Console name="STDOUT" target="SYSTEM_OUT">
      <PatternLayout pattern="%m%n"/>
    </Console>
    <Failover name="Failover" primary="RollingFile" suppressExceptions="false">
      <Failovers>
        <appender-ref ref="Console"/>
      </Failovers>
    </Failover>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="Failover"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <a name="FileAppender"/>
        <subsection name="FileAppender">
          <p>The FileAppender is an OutputStreamAppender that writes to the File named in the fileName parameter. The
            FileAppender uses a FileManager (which extends OutputStreamManager) to actually perform the file I/O. While
            FileAppenders from different Configurations cannot be shared, the FileManagers can be if the Manager is
            accessible. For example, two webapps in a servlet container can have their own configuration and safely
            write to the same file if Log4J is in a ClassLoader that is common to both of them.</p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>append</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When true - the default, records will be appended to the end of the file. When set to false,
                the file will be cleared before new reocrds are written.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>bufferedIO</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When true - the default, records will be written to a buffer and the data will be written to
                disk when the buffer is full or, if immediateFlush is set, when the record is written.
                File locking cannot be used with bufferedIO. Performance tests have shown that using buffered I/O
                significantly improves performance, even if immediateFlush is enabled.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
              may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>fileName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the file to write to. If the file, or any of its parent directories, do not exist,
                they will be created.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>immediateFlush</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When set to true, each write will be followed by a flush. This will guarantee the data is written
                to disk but could impact performance.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>layout</td>
              <td>Layout</td>
              <td>The Layout to use to format the LogEvent</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>locking</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When set to true, I/O operations will occur only while the file lock is held allowing FileAppenders
                in multiple JVMs and potentially multiple hosts to write to the same file simultaneously. This
                will significantly impact performance so should be used carefully. Furthermore, on many systems
                the file lock is "advisory" meaning that other applications can perform operations on the file
                without acquiring a lock. The default value is false.</td>
            </tr>

            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">FileAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
           <p>
            Here is a sample File configuration:

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <File name="MyFile" fileName="logs/app.log">
      <PatternLayout>
        <pattern>%d %p %C{1.} [%t] %m%n</pattern>
      </PatternLayout>
    </File>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="MyFile"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <a name="FlumeAppender"/>
        <subsection name="FlumeAppender">
          <p><i>This is an optional component supplied in a separate jar.</i></p>
          <p><a href="http://flume.apache.org/index.html">Apache Flume</a> is a distributed, reliable,
            and available system for efficiently collecting, aggregating, and moving large amounts of log data
            from many different sources to a centralized data store. The FlumeAppender takes LogEvents and sends
            them to a Flume agent as serialized Avro events for consumption.</p>
          <p>
            The Flume Appender supports two modes of operation.
            <ol>
              <li>It can act as a remote Flume client which sends Flume events via Avro to a Flume Agent configured
              with an Avro Source.</li>
              <li>It can act as an embedded Flume Agent where Flume events pass directly into Flume for processing.</li>
            </ol>
            Usage as an embedded agent will cause the messages to be directly passed to the Flume Channel and then
            control will be immediately returned to the application. All interaction with remote agents will occur
            asynchronously. Setting the "embedded" attribute to "true" will force the use of the embedded agent. In
            addition, configuring agent properties in the appender configuration will also cause the embedded agent
            to be used.
          </p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>agents</td>
              <td>Agent[]</td>
              <td>An array of Agents to which the logging events should be sent. If more than one agent is specified
                the first Agent will be the primary and subsequent Agents will be used in the order specified as
                secondaries should the primary Agent fail. Each Agent definition supplies the Agents host and port.
                The specification of agents and properties are mutually exclusive. If both are configured an
                error will result.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>agentRetries</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>The number of times the agent should be retried before failing to a secondary.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>batchSize</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>Specifies the number of events that should be sent as a batch. The default is 1. <i>This
                parameter only applies to the Flume NG Appender.</i></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>compress</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When set to true the message body will be compressed using gzip</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>dataDir</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>Directory where the Flume write ahead log should be written. Valid only when embedded is set
                to true and Agent elements are used instead of Property elements.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>embedded</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When set to true the embedded Flume agent will be used. When Agent elements are used the events
                will be sent to a file channel and then routed to a FailoverSinkProcessor which will use
                each configured agent in the order they are declared.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
              may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>eventPrefix</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The character string to prepend to each event attribute in order to distinguish it from MDC attributes.
                The default is an empty string.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>flumeEventFactory</td>
              <td>FlumeEventFactory</td>
              <td>Factory that generates the Flume events from Log4j events. The default factory is the
                FlumeAvroAppender itself.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>layout</td>
              <td>Layout</td>
              <td>The Layout to use to format the LogEvent. If no layout is specified RFC5424Layout will be used.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>mdcExcludes</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>A comma separated list of mdc keys that should be excluded from the FlumeEvent. This is mutually
                exclusive with the mdcIncludes attribute.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>mdcIncludes</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>A comma separated list of mdc keys that should be included in the FlumeEvent. Any keys in the MDC
                not found in the list will be excluded. This option is mutually exclusive with the mdcExcludes
                attribute.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>mdcRequired</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>A comma separated list of mdc keys that must be present in the MDC. If a key is not present a
                LoggingException will be thrown.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>mdcPrefix</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>A string that should be prepended to each MDC key in order to distinguish it from event attributes.
                The default string is "mdc:".</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>properties</td>
              <td>Property[]</td>
              <td>One or more Property elements that are used to configure the Flume Agent. The properties must be
                configured without the agent name (the appender name is used for this) and no sources can be
                configured. All other Flume configuration properties are allowed. Specifying both Agent and Property
                elements will result in an error.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>reconnectionDelay</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>The number of milliseconds the application should wait before trying again to connect to the
                agent.</td>
            </tr>

            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">FlumeAvroAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
            <p>
              A sample FlumeAppender configuration that is configured with a primary and a secondary agent,
              compresses the body, and formats the body using the RFC5424Layout:

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <Flume name="eventLogger" suppressExceptions="false" compress="true">
      <Agent host="192.168.10.101" port="8800"/>
      <Agent host="192.168.10.102" port="8800"/>
      <RFC5424Layout enterpriseNumber="18060" includeMDC="true" appName="MyApp"/>
    </Flume>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="eventLogger"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
          <p>
            A sample FlumeAppender configuration that is configured with a primary and a secondary agent,
            compresses the body, formats the body using RFC5424Layout and passes the events to an embedded Flume
            Agent.
          </p>
          <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <Flume name="eventLogger" suppressExceptions="false" compress="true" embedded="true">
      <Agent host="192.168.10.101" port="8800"/>
      <Agent host="192.168.10.102" port="8800"/>
      <RFC5424Layout enterpriseNumber="18060" includeMDC="true" appName="MyApp"/>
    </Flume>
    <Console name="STDOUT">
      <PatternLayout pattern="%d [%p] %c %m%n"/>
    </Console>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <logger name="EventLogger" level="info">
      <appender-ref ref="eventLogger"/>
    </logger>
    <root level="warn">
      <appender-ref ref="STDOUT"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          <p>
            A sample FlumeAppender configuration that is configured with a primary and a secondary agent using
            Flume configuration properties, compresses the body, formats the body using RFC5424Layout and passes the
            events to an embedded Flume Agent.
          </p>
          <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="error" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <Flume name="eventLogger" suppressExceptions="false" compress="true" embedded="true">
      <Property name="channels">file</Property>
      <Property name="channels.file.type">file</Property>
      <Property name="channels.file.checkpointDir">target/file-channel/checkpoint</Property>
      <Property name="channels.file.dataDirs">target/file-channel/data</Property>
      <Property name="sinks">agent1 agent2</Property>
      <Property name="sinks.agent1.channel">file</Property>
      <Property name="sinks.agent1.type">avro</Property>
      <Property name="sinks.agent1.hostname">192.168.10.101</Property>
      <Property name="sinks.agent1.port">8800</Property>
      <Property name="sinks.agent1.batch-size">100</Property>
      <Property name="sinks.agent2.channel">file</Property>
      <Property name="sinks.agent2.type">avro</Property>
      <Property name="sinks.agent2.hostname">192.168.10.102</Property>
      <Property name="sinks.agent2.port">8800</Property>
      <Property name="sinks.agent2.batch-size">100</Property>
      <Property name="sinkgroups">group1</Property>
      <Property name="sinkgroups.group1.sinks">agent1 agent2</Property>
      <Property name="sinkgroups.group1.processor.type">failover</Property>
      <Property name="sinkgroups.group1.processor.priority.agent1">10</Property>
      <Property name="sinkgroups.group1.processor.priority.agent2">5</Property>
      <RFC5424Layout enterpriseNumber="18060" includeMDC="true" appName="MyApp"/>
    </Flume>
    <Console name="STDOUT">
      <PatternLayout pattern="%d [%p] %c %m%n"/>
    </Console>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <logger name="EventLogger" level="info">
      <appender-ref ref="eventLogger"/>
    </logger>
    <root level="warn">
      <appender-ref ref="STDOUT"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
        </subsection>
        <a name="JMSQueueAppender"/>
        <subsection name="JMSQueueAppender">
          <p>The JMSQueueAppender sends the formatted log event to a JMS Queue.</p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>factoryBindingName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name to locate in the Context that provides the
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javaee/5/api/javax/jms/QueueConnectionFactory.html">QueueConnectionFactory</a>.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>factoryName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The fully qualified class name that should be used to define the Initial Context Factory as
                defined in <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/javax/naming/Context.html#INITIAL_CONTEXT_FACTORY">INITIAL_CONTEXT_FACTORY</a>.
                If no value is provided the
                default InitialContextFactory will be used. If a factoryName is specified without a providerURL
                a warning message will be logged as this is likely to cause problems.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
              may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>layout</td>
              <td>Layout</td>
              <td>The Layout to use to format the LogEvent. If no layout is specified SerializedLayout will be used.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>password</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The password to use to create the queue connection.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>providerURL</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The URL of the provider to use as defined by
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/javax/naming/Context.html#PROVIDER_URL">PROVIDER_URL</a>.
                If this value is null the default system provider will be used.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>queueBindingName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name to use to locate the <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javaee/5/api/javax/jms/Queue.html">Queue</a>.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>securityPrincipalName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the identity of the Principal as specified by
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/javax/naming/Context.html#SECURITY_PRINCIPAL">SECURITY_PRINCIPAL</a>.
                If a securityPrincipalName is specified without securityCredentials a warning message will be
                logged as this is likely to cause problems.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>securityCredentials</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The security credentials for the principal as specified by
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/javax/naming/Context.html#SECURITY_CREDENTIALS">SECURITY_CREDENTIALS</a>.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>urlPkgPrefixes</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>A colon-separated list of package prefixes for the class name of the factory class that will create
                a URL context factory as defined by
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/javax/naming/Context.html#URL_PKG_PREFIXES">URL_PKG_PREFIXES</a>.</td>
            </tr>
             <tr>
              <td>userName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The user id used to create the queue connection.</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">JMSQueueAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
           <p>
            Here is a sample JMSQueueAppender configuration:

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <JMSQueue name="jmsQueue" queueBindingName="MyQueue"
              factoryBindingName="MyQueueConnectionFactory"/>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="jmsQueue"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <a name="JMSTopicAppender"/>
        <subsection name="JMSTopicAppender">
          <p>The JMSTopicAppender sends the formatted log event to a JMS Topic.</p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>factoryBindingName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name to locate in the Context that provides the
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javaee/5/api/javax/jms/TopicConnectionFactory.html">TopicConnectionFactory</a>.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>factoryName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The fully qualified class name that should be used to define the Initial Context Factory as
                defined in <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/javax/naming/Context.html#INITIAL_CONTEXT_FACTORY">INITIAL_CONTEXT_FACTORY</a>.
                If no value is provided the
                default InitialContextFactory will be used. If a factoryName is specified without a providerURL
                a warning message will be logged as this is likely to cause problems.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
              may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>layout</td>
              <td>Layout</td>
              <td>The Layout to use to format the LogEvent. If no layout is specified SerializedLayout will be used.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>password</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The password to use to create the queue connection.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>providerURL</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The URL of the provider to use as defined by
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/javax/naming/Context.html#PROVIDER_URL">PROVIDER_URL</a>.
                If this value is null the default system provider will be used.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>topicBindingName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name to use to locate the
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javaee/5/api/javax/jms/Topic.html">Topic</a>.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>securityPrincipalName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the identity of the Principal as specified by
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/javax/naming/Context.html#SECURITY_PRINCIPAL">SECURITY_PRINCIPAL</a>.
                If a securityPrincipalName is specified without securityCredentials a warning message will be
                logged as this is likely to cause problems.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>securityCredentials</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The security credentials for the principal as specified by
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/javax/naming/Context.html#SECURITY_CREDENTIALS">SECURITY_CREDENTIALS</a>.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>urlPkgPrefixes</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>A colon-separated list of package prefixes for the class name of the factory class that will create
                a URL context factory as defined by
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/javax/naming/Context.html#URL_PKG_PREFIXES">URL_PKG_PREFIXES</a>.</td>
            </tr>
             <tr>
              <td>userName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The user id used to create the queue connection.</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">JMSTopicAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
           <p>
            Here is a sample JMSTopicAppender configuration:

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <JMSTopic name="jmsTopic" topicBindingName="MyTopic"
              factoryBindingName="MyTopicConnectionFactory"/>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="jmsQueue"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <a name="OutputStreamAppender"/>
        <subsection name="OutputStreamAppender">
          The OutputStreamAppender provides the base for many of the other Appenders such as the File and Socket
          appenders that write the event to an Output Stream. It cannot be directly configured. Support for
          immediateFlush and buffering is provided by the OutputStreamAppender. The OutputStreamAppender uses an
          OutputStreamManager to handle the actual I/O, allowing the stream to be shared by Appenders in multiple
          configurations.
        </subsection>
        <a name="RewriteAppender"/>
        <subsection name="RewriteAppender">
          <p>
            The RewriteAppender allows the LogEvent to manipulated before it is processed by another Appender. This
            can be used to mask sensitive information such as passwords or to inject information into each event.
            The RewriteAppender must be configured with a <a href="RewritePolicy">RewritePolicy</a>. The
            RewriteAppender should be configured after any Appenders it references to allow it to shut down properly.
          </p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>appender-ref</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appenders to call after the LogEvent has been manipulated. Multiple appender-ref
                elements can be configured.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
              may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>rewritePolicy</td>
              <td>RewritePolciy</td>
              <td>The RewritePolicy that will manipulate the LogEvent.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">RewriteAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
          <h4>RewritePolicy</h4>
            <p>
              RewritePolicy is an interface that allows implementations to inspect and possibly modify LogEvents
              before they are passed to Appender. RewritePolicy declares a single method named rewrite that must
              be implemented. The method is passed the LogEvent and can return the same event or create a new one.
            </p>
            <h5>MapRewritePolicy</h5>
              <p>
                MapRewritePolicy will evaluate LogEvents that contain a MapMessage and will add or update
                elements of the Map.
              </p>
              <table>
                <tr>
                  <th>Parameter Name</th>
                  <th>Type</th>
                  <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>mode</td>
                  <td>String</td>
                  <td>"Add" or "Update"</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>keyValuePair</td>
                  <td>KeyValuePair[]</td>
                  <td>An array of keys and their values.</td>
                </tr>
              </table>
           <p>
             The following configuration shows a RewriteAppender configured to add a product key and its value
             to the MapMessage.:

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <Console name="STDOUT" target="SYSTEM_OUT">
      <PatternLayout pattern="%m%n"/>
    </Console>
    <Rewrite name="rewrite">
      <appender-ref ref="STDOUT"/>
      <MapRewritePolicy mode="Add">
        <KeyValuePair key="product" value="TestProduct"/>
      </MapRewritePolicy>
    </Rewrite>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="Rewrite"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
          <h5>PropertiesRewritePolicy</h5>
          <p>
            PropertiesRewritePolicy will add properties configured on the policy to the ThreadContext Map
            being logged. The properties will not be added to the actual ThreadContext Map. The property
            values may contain variables that will be evaluated when the configuration is processed as
            well as when the event is logged.
          </p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>properties</td>
              <td>Property[]</td>
              <td>One of more Property elements to define the keys and values to be added to the ThreadContext Map.</td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <p>
            The following configuration shows a RewriteAppender configured to add a product key and its value
            to the MapMessage.:

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <Console name="STDOUT" target="SYSTEM_OUT">
      <PatternLayout pattern="%m%n"/>
    </Console>
    <Rewrite name="rewrite">
      <appender-ref ref="STDOUT"/>
      <PropertiesRewritePolicy>
        <Property key="user">${sys:user.name}</Property>
        <Property key="env">${sys:environment}</Property>
      </PropertiesRewritePolicy>
    </Rewrite>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="Rewrite"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <a name="RollingFileAppender"/>
        <subsection name="RollingFileAppender">
          <p>The RollingFileAppender is an OutputStreamAppender that writes to the File named in the fileName parameter
            and rolls the file over according the TriggeringPolicy and the RolloverPolicy. The
            RollingFileAppender uses a RollingFileManager (which extends OutputStreamManager) to actually perform the
            file I/O and perform the rollover. While RolloverFileAppenders from different Configurations cannot be
            shared, the RollingFileManagers can be if the Manager is accessible. For example, two webapps in a
            servlet container can have their own configuration and safely
            write to the same file if Log4J is in a ClassLoader that is common to both of them.</p>
          <p>
            A RollingFileAppender requires a <a href="#TriggeringPolicies">TriggeringPolicy</a> and a
            <a href="#RolloverStrategies">RolloverStrategy</a>. The triggering policy determines if a rollover should
            be performed while the RolloverStrategy defines how the rollover should be done. If no RolloverStrategy
            is configured, RollingFileAppender will use the <a href="DefaultRolloverStrategy">DefaultRolloverStrategy</a>.
          </p>
          <p>
            File locking is not supported by the RollingFileAppender.
          </p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>append</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When true - the default, records will be appended to the end of the file. When set to false,
                the file will be cleared before new reocrds are written.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>bufferedIO</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When true - the default, records will be written to a buffer and the data will be written to
                disk when the buffer is full or, if immediateFlush is set, when the record is written.
                File locking cannot be used with bufferedIO. Performance tests have shown that using buffered I/O
                significantly improves performance, even if immediateFlush is enabled.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
              may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>fileName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the file to write to. If the file, or any of its parent directories, do not exist,
                they will be created.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filePattern</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The pattern of the file name of the archived log file. The format of the pattern should is
                dependent on the RolloverPolicy that is used. The DefaultRolloverPolicy will accept both
                a date/time pattern compatible with
                <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/java/text/SimpleDateFormat.html">SimpleDateFormat</a>
                and and/or a %i which represents an integer counter. The pattern also supports interpolation at
                runtime so any of the Lookups (such as the <a href="./lookups.html#DateLookup">DateLookup</a> can
                be included in the pattern.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>immediateFlush</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When set to true, each write will be followed by a flush. This will guarantee the data is written
                to disk but could impact performance.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>layout</td>
              <td>Layout</td>
              <td>The Layout to use to format the LogEvent</td>
            </tr>

            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>policy</td>
              <td>TriggeringPolicy</td>
              <td>The policy to use to determine if a rollover should occur.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>strategy</td>
              <td>RolloverStrategy</td>
              <td>The strategy to use to determine the name and location of the archive file.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">RollingFileAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
          <a name="TriggeringPolicies"/>
          <h4>Triggering Policies</h4>
            <h5>Composite Triggering Policy</h5>
              <p>
                The CompositeTriggeringPolicy combines multiple triggering policies and returns true if any
                of the configured policies return true. The CompositeTriggeringPolicy is configured simply
                by wrapping other policies in a "Policies" element.
              </p>
            <h5>OnStartup Triggering Policy</h5>
              <p>
                The OnStartup policy takes no parameters and causes a rollover if the log file is older than the
                current JVM's start time.
              </p>
            <h5>SizeBased Triggering Policy</h5>
              <p>
                Causes a rollover once the file has reached the specified size. The size can be specified in bytes,
                KB, MB or GB.
              </p>
            <h5>TimeBased Triggering Policy</h5>
              <p>
                Causes a rollover once the date/time pattern no longer applies to the active file. This policy
                accepts an "increment" attribute which indicates how frequently the rollover should occur based on the
                time pattern and a "modulate" boolean attribute.
              </p>
                <table>
                  <tr>
                    <th>Parameter Name</th>
                    <th>Type</th>
                    <th>Description</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>interval</td>
                    <td>integer</td>
                    <td>How often a rollover should occur based on the most specific time unit in the date pattern.
                      For example, with a date pattern with hours as the most specific item and and increment of 4 rollovers
                      would occur every 4 hours.
                      The default value is 1.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>modulate</td>
                    <td>boolean</td>
                    <td>Indicates whether the interval should be adjusted to cause the next rollover to occur on
                      the interval boundary. For example, if the item is hours, the current hour is 3 am and the
                      interval is 4 then then the first rollover will occur at 4 am and then next ones will occur at
                      8 am, noon, 4pm, etc.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <caption align="top">TimeBasedTriggeringPolicy Parameters</caption>
                </table>
          <a name="RolloverStrategies"/>
          <h4>Rollover Strategies</h4>
            <a name="DefaultRolloverStrategy"/>
            <h5>Default Rollover Strategy</h5>
              <p>
                The default rollover strategy accepts both a date/time pattern and an integer from the filePattern
                attribute specified on the RollingFileAppender itself. If the date/time pattern
                is present it will be replaced with the current date and time values. If the pattern contains an integer
                it will be incremented on each rollover. If the pattern contains both a date/time and integer
                in the pattern the integer will be incremented until the result of the date/time pattern changes. If
                the file pattern ends with ".gz" or ".zip" the resulting archive will be compressed using the
                compression scheme that matches the suffix. The pattern may also contain lookup references that
                can be resolved at runtime such as is shown in the example below.
              </p>
              <p>The default rollover strategy supports two variations for incrementing the counter. The first is
                the "fixed window" strategy. To illustrate how it works, suppose that the min attribute is set to 1,
                the max attribute is set to 3, the file name is "foo.log", and the file name pattern is "foo-%i.log".
              </p>

              <table>
                <tr>
                  <th>Number of rollovers</th>
                  <th>Active output target</th>
                  <th>Archived log files</th>
                  <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>foo.log</td>
                  <td>-</td>
                  <td>All logging is going to the initial file.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>1</td>
                  <td>foo.log</td>
                  <td>foo-1.log</td>
                  <td>During the first rollover foo.log is renamed to foo-1.log. A new foo.log file is created and
                  starts being written to.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>2</td>
                  <td>foo.log</td>
                  <td>foo-1.log, foo-2.log</td>
                  <td>During the second rollover foo-1.log is renamed to foo-2.log and foo.log is renamed to
                    foo-1.log. A new foo.log file is created and starts being written to.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>3</td>
                  <td>foo.log</td>
                  <td>foo-1.log, foo-2.log, foo-3.log</td>
                  <td>During the third rollover foo-2.log is renamed to foo-3.log, foo-1.log is renamed to foo-2.log and
                    foo.log is renamed to foo-1.log. A new foo.log file is created and starts being written to.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>4</td>
                  <td>foo.log</td>
                  <td>foo-1.log, foo-2.log, foo-3.log</td>
                  <td>In the fourth and subsequent rollovers, foo-3.log is deleted, foo-2.log is renamed to foo-3.log,
                    foo-1.log is renamed to foo-2.log and foo.log is renamed to foo-1.log. A new foo.log file is
                    created and starts being written to.</td>
                </tr>
              </table>
              <p>By way of contrast, when the the fileIndex attribute is set to "max" but all the other settings
                are the same the following actions will be performed.
              </p>
              <table>
                <tr>
                  <th>Number of rollovers</th>
                  <th>Active output target</th>
                  <th>Archived log files</th>
                  <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>foo.log</td>
                  <td>-</td>
                  <td>All logging is going to the initial file.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>1</td>
                  <td>foo.log</td>
                  <td>foo-1.log</td>
                  <td>During the first rollover foo.log is renamed to foo-1.log. A new foo.log file is created and
                    starts being written to.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>2</td>
                  <td>foo.log</td>
                  <td>foo-1.log, foo-2.log</td>
                  <td>During the second rollover foo.log is renamed to foo-2.log. A new foo.log file is created
                    and starts being written to.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>3</td>
                  <td>foo.log</td>
                  <td>foo-1.log, foo-2.log, foo-3.log</td>
                  <td>During the third rollover foo.log is renamed to foo-3.log. A new foo.log file is created and
                    starts being written to.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>4</td>
                  <td>foo.log</td>
                  <td>foo-1.log, foo-2.log, foo-3.log</td>
                  <td>In the fourth and subsequent rollovers, foo-1.log is deleted, foo-2.log is renamed to foo-1.log,
                    foo-3.log is renamed to foo-2.log and foo.log is renamed to foo-3.log. A new foo.log file is
                    created and starts being written to.</td>
                </tr>
              </table>
              <table>
                <tr>
                  <th>Parameter Name</th>
                  <th>Type</th>
                  <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>fileIndex</td>
                  <td>String</td>
                  <td>If set to "max" (the default), files with a higher index will be newer than files with a
                    smaller index. If set to "min", file renaming and the counter will follow the Fixed Window strategy
                    described above.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>min</td>
                  <td>integer</td>
                  <td>The minimum value of the counter. The default value is 1.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>max</td>
                  <td>integer</td>
                  <td>The maximum value of the counter. Once this values is reached older archives will be
                    deleted on subsequent rollovers.</td>
                </tr>
                <caption align="top">DefaultRolloverStrategy Parameters</caption>
              </table>

          <p>
            Below is a sample configuration that uses a RollingFileAppender with both the time and size based
            triggering policies, will create up to 7 archives on the same day (1-7) that are stored in a directory
            based on the current year and month, and will compress each
            archive using gzip:

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <RollingFile name="RollingFile" fileName="logs/app.log"
                 filePattern="logs/$${date:yyyy-MM}/app-%d{MM-dd-yyyy}-%i.log.gz">
      <PatternLayout>
        <pattern>%d %p %C{1.} [%t] %m%n</pattern>
      </PatternLayout>
      <Policies>
        <TimeBasedTriggeringPolicy />
        <SizeBasedTriggeringPolicy size="250 MB"/>
      </Policies>
    </RollingFile>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="RollingFile"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
          <p>
            This second example shows a rollover strategy that will keep up to 20 files before removing them.
          <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <RollingFile name="RollingFile" fileName="logs/app.log"
                 filePattern="logs/$${date:yyyy-MM}/app-%d{MM-dd-yyyy}-%i.log.gz">
      <PatternLayout>
        <pattern>%d %p %C{1.} [%t] %m%n</pattern>
      </PatternLayout>
      <Policies>
        <TimeBasedTriggeringPolicy />
        <SizeBasedTriggeringPolicy size="250 MB"/>
      </Policies>
      <DefaultRolloverStrategy max="20"/>
    </RollingFile>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="RollingFile"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
        </p>
          <p>
            Below is a sample configuration that uses a RollingFileAppender with both the time and size based
            triggering policies, will create up to 7 archives on the same day (1-7) that are stored in a directory
            based on the current year and month, and will compress each
            archive using gzip and will roll every 6 hours when the hour is divisible by 6:

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <RollingFile name="RollingFile" fileName="logs/app.log"
                 filePattern="logs/$${date:yyyy-MM}/app-%d{yyyy-MM-dd-HH}-%i.log.gz">
      <PatternLayout>
        <pattern>%d %p %C{1.} [%t] %m%n</pattern>
      </PatternLayout>
      <Policies>
        <TimeBasedTriggeringPolicy interval="6" modulate="true"/>
        <SizeBasedTriggeringPolicy size="250 MB"/>
      </Policies>
    </RollingFile>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="RollingFile"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <a name="RoutingAppender"/>
        <subsection name="RoutingAppender">
           <p>
             The RoutingAppender evaluates LogEvents and then routes them to a subordinate Appender. The target
             Appender may be an appender previously configured and may be referenced by its name or the
             Appender can be dynamically created as needed. The RoutingAppender should be configured after any
             Appenders it references to allow it to shut down properly.
          </p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
              may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>rewritePolicy</td>
              <td>RewritePolciy</td>
              <td>The RewritePolicy that will manipulate the LogEvent.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>routes</td>
              <td>Routes</td>
              <td>Contains one or more Route declarations to identify the criteria for choosing Appenders.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">RoutingAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
          <h4>Routes</h4>
            <p>
              The Routes element accepts a single, required attribute named "pattern". The pattern is evaluated
              against all the registered Lookups and the result is used to select a Route. Each Route may be
              configured with a key. If the key matches the result of evaluating the pattern then that Route
              will be selected. If no key is specified on a Route then that Route is the default. Only one Route
              can be configured as the default.
            </p>
            <p>
              Each Route must reference an Appender. If the Route contains an appender-ref attribute then the
              Route will reference an Appender that was defined in the configuration. If the Route contains an
              Appender definition then an Appender will be created within the context of the RoutingAppender and
              will be reused each time a matching Appender name is referenced through a Route.
            </p>
          <p>
            Below is a sample configuration that uses a RoutingAppender to route all Audit events to
            a FlumeAppender and all other events will be routed to a RollingFileAppender that captures only
            the specific event type. Note that the AuditAppender was predefined while the RollingFileAppenders
            are created as needed.

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <Flume name="AuditLogger" suppressExceptions="false" compress="true">
      <Agent host="192.168.10.101" port="8800"/>
      <Agent host="192.168.10.102" port="8800"/>
      <RFC5424Layout enterpriseNumber="18060" includeMDC="true" appName="MyApp"/>
    </Flume>
    <Routing name="Routing">
      <Routes pattern="$${sd:type}">
        <Route>
          <RollingFile name="Rolling-${sd:type}" fileName="${sd:type}.log"
                       filePattern="${sd:type}.%i.log.gz">
            <PatternLayout>
              <pattern>%d %p %C{1.} [%t] %m%n</pattern>
            </PatternLayout>
            <SizeBasedTriggeringPolicy size="500" />
          </RollingFile>
        </Route>
        <Route appender-ref="AuditLogger" key="Audit"/>
      </Routes>
    </Routing>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="Routing"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <a name="SMTPAppender"/>
        <subsection name="SMTPAppender">
          <p>
            Sends an e-mail when a specific logging event occurs, typically on errors or fatal errors.
          </p>
          <p>
            The number of logging events delivered in this e-mail depend on the value of
            <b>BufferSize</b> option. The <code>SMTPAppender</code> keeps only the last
            <code>BufferSize</code> logging events in its cyclic buffer. This keeps
            memory requirements at a reasonable level while still delivering useful
            application context.
          </p>
          <p>
            The default behavior is to trigger sending an email whenever an ERROR or higher
            severity event is logged and to format it as HTML. The circumstances on when the
            email is sent can be controlled by setting one or more filters on the Appender.
            As with other Appenders, the formatting can be controlled by specifying a Layout
            for the Appender.
          </p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>bcc</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The comma-separated list of BCC email addresses.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>cc</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The comma-separated list of CC email addresses.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>bufferSize</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>The maximum number of log events to be buffered for inclusion in the message. Defaults to 512.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
                may be used by using a CompositeFilter.
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>from</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The email address of the sender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>layout</td>
              <td>Layout</td>
              <td>The Layout to use to format the LogEvent. The default is SerializedLayout.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>replyTo</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The comma-separated list of reply-to email addresses.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>smtpDebug</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When set to true enables session debugging on STDOUT. Defaults to false.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>smtpHost</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The SMTP hostname to send to. This parameter is required.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>smtpPassword</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The password required to authenticate against the SMTP server.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>smtpPort</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>The SMTP port to send to. </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>smtpProtocol</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The SMTP transport protocol (such as "smtps", defaults to "smtp").</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>smtpUsername</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The username required to authenticate against the SMTP server.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>to</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The comma-separated list of recipient email addresses.</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">SMTPAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
          <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <SMTP name="Mail" suppressExceptions="false" subject="Error Log" to="errors@logging.apache.org"
      from="test@logging.apache.org" smtpHost="localhost" smtpPort="25" bufferSize="50">
    </SMTP>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="Mail"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
        </subsection>
        <a name="SocketAppender"/>
        <subsection name="SocketAppender">
          <p>
            The SocketAppender is an OutputStreamAppender that writes its output to a remote destination
            specified by a host and port. The data can be sent over either TCP or UDP and can be sent in any format.
            The default format is to send a Serialized LogEvent. Log4j 2 contains a SocketServer which is capable
            of receiving serialized LogEvents and routing them through the logging system on the server.
          </p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
              may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>host</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name or address of the system that is listening for log events. This parameter is required.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>immediateFlush</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When set to true, each write will be followed by a flush. This will guarantee the data is written
                to disk but could impact performance.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>layout</td>
              <td>Layout</td>
              <td>The Layout to use to format the LogEvent. The default is SerializedLayout.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>port</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>The port on the host that is listening for log events. This parameter must be specified.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>protocol</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>"TCP" or "UDP". This parameter is required.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>reconnectionDelay</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>If set to a value greater than 0, after an error the SocketManager will attempt to reconnect to
                the server after waiting the specified number of milliseconds. If the reconnect fails then
                an exception will be thrown (which can be caught by the application if suppressExceptions is
                set to false).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">SocketAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>

          <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <Socket name="socket" host="localhost" port="9500">
      <SerializedLayout />
    </Socket>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="socket"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
        </subsection>
        <a name="SyslogAppender"/>
        <subsection name="SyslogAppender">
          <p>
            The SyslogAppender is a SocketAppender that writes its output to a remote destination
            specified by a host and port in a format that conforms with either the BSD Syslog format or the RFC 5424
            format. The data can be sent over either TCP or UDP.
          </p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Parameter Name</th>
              <th>Type</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>appName</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The value to use as the APP-NAME in the RFC 5424 syslog record.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>charset</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The character set to use when converting the syslog String to a byte array. The String must be
                a valid <a href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/api/java/nio/charset/Charset.html">Charset</a>.
                If not specified, the default system Charset will be used.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>enterpriseNumber</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>The IANA enterprise number as described in
                <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5424#section-7.2.2">RFC 5424</a></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filter</td>
              <td>Filter</td>
              <td>A Filter to determine if the event should be handled by this Appender. More than one Filter
              may be used by using a CompositeFilter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>facility</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The facility is used to try to classify the message. The facility option must be set to one of
                "KERN", "USER", "MAIL", "DAEMON", "AUTH", "SYSLOG", "LPR", "NEWS", "UUCP", "CRON", "AUTHPRIV",
                "FTP", "NTP", "AUDIT", "ALERT", "CLOCK", "LOCAL0", "LOCAL1", "LOCAL2", "LOCAL3", "LOCAL4", "LOCAL5",
                "LOCAL6", or "LOCAL7". These values may be specified as upper or lower case characters.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>format</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>If set to "RFC5424" the data will be formatted in accordance with RFC 5424. Otherwise, it will
                be formatted as a BSD Syslog record. Note that although BSD Syslog records are required to be
                1024 bytes or shorter the SyslogLayout does not truncate them. The RFC5424Layout also does not
                truncate records since the receiver must accept records of up to 2048 bytes and may accept records
                that are longer.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>host</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name or address of the system that is listening for log events. This parameter is required.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>id</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The default structured data id to use when formatting according to RFC 5424. If the LogEvent contains
                a StructuredDataMessage the id from the Message will be used instead of this value.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>immediateFlush</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>When set to true, each write will be followed by a flush. This will guarantee the data is written
                to disk but could impact performance.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>includeMDC</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>Indicates whether data from the ThreadContextMap will be included in the RFC 5424 Syslog record.
                Defaults to true.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>mdcExcludes</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>A comma separated list of mdc keys that should be excluded from the LogEvent. This is mutually
                exclusive with the mdcIncludes attribute. This attribute only applies to RFC 5424 syslog records.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>mdcIncludes</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>A comma separated list of mdc keys that should be included in the FlumeEvent. Any keys in the MDC
                not found in the list will be excluded. This option is mutually exclusive with the mdcExcludes
                attribute. This attribute only applies to RFC 5424 syslog records.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>mdcRequired</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>A comma separated list of mdc keys that must be present in the MDC. If a key is not present a
                LoggingException will be thrown. This attribute only applies to RFC 5424 syslog records.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>mdcPrefix</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>A string that should be prepended to each MDC key in order to distinguish it from event attributes.
                The default string is "mdc:". This attribute only applies to RFC 5424 syslog records.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>messageId</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The default value to be used in the MSGID field of RFC 5424 syslog records. </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>name</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>The name of the Appender.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>newLine</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>If true, a newline will be appended to the end of the syslog record. The default is false.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>port</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>The port on the host that is listening for log events. This parameter must be specified.</td>
            </tr>

            <tr>
              <td>protocol</td>
              <td>String</td>
              <td>"TCP" or "UDP". This parameter is required.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>reconnectionDelay</td>
              <td>integer</td>
              <td>If set to a value greater than 0, after an error the SocketManager will attempt to reconnect to
                the server after waiting the specified number of milliseconds. If the reconnect fails then
                an exception will be thrown (which can be caught by the application if suppressExceptions is
                set to false).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>suppressExceptions</td>
              <td>boolean</td>
              <td>The default is true, causing exceptions to be internally logged and then ignored. When set to
                false exceptions will be percolated to the caller.</td>
            </tr>
            <caption align="top">SyslogAppender Parameters</caption>
          </table>
          <p>
            A sample syslogAppender configuration that is configured with two SyslogAppenders, one using the BSD
            format and one using RFC 5424.

            <pre class="prettyprint linenums"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration status="warn" name="MyApp" packages="">
  <appenders>
    <Syslog name="bsd" host="localhost" port="514" protocol="TCP"/>
    <Syslog name="RFC5424" format="RFC5424" host="localhost" port="8514"
            protocol="TCP" appName="MyApp" includeMDC="true"
            facility="LOCAL0" enterpriseNumber="18060" newLine="true"
            messageId="Audit" id="App"/>
  </appenders>
  <loggers>
    <logger name="com.mycorp" level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="RFC5424"/>
    </logger>
    <root level="error">
      <appender-ref ref="bsd"/>
    </root>
  </loggers>
</configuration>]]></pre>
          </p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
  </body>
</document>
