<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Changes</title>
    <author email="rgoers@apache.org">Ralph Goers</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <release version="2.0-beta4" date="2012-01-28" description="Bug fixes and enhancements">
      <action issue="LOG4J2-156" dev="ggregory" type="fix" due-to="Andreas Born">
        LocalizedMessageTest fails on linux system.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-152" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="Remko Popma">
        RollingFileAppender's FileRenameAction was throwing a NullPointerException if no directory was specified
        on the target file name.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-150" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Convert all System.getProperty calls to use PropertiesUtil to suppress SecurityExceptions.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-147" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="William Burns">
        ThreadContextMapFilter was matching on the key instead of the value of the key.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Allow FlumeAvroManager to initialize even if it cannot connect to an agent.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-149" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="Scott Severtson">
        SMTPAppender will only cache filtered events.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-145" dev="ggregory" type="fix">
        Add missing serial version IDs.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-144" dev="ggregory" type="fix">
        NullPointerException in RFC5424Layout.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-143" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        MessagePatternConverter now returns "null" if the log message is null.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-142" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Serialized LogEvents were not reset in the output stream causing them to deserialize incorrectly.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-139" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Fix null pointer exception in SocketAppender if no protocol is specified. The protocol will default
        to TCP for the SocketAppender and UDP for the SyslogAppender.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Added Log4j 2 to SLF4J adapter.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-140" dev="ggregory" type="fix" due-to="Joern Huxhorn">
        Typo in documentation of SocketAppender.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-137" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Fix hang in Dumbster SMTP test server.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-136" dev="rgoers" type="update" due-to="Scott Severtson">
        Allow newlines to be escaped in Syslog and RFC5424 layouts. Allow Throwables to be included in
        the output from RFC5424Layout.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-131" dev="rgoers" type="add" due-to="Scott Severtson">
        Add SMTPAppender.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-130" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        PatternLayout should format throwables without requiring a converter.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Added hostName and contextName to property map.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-135" dev="ggregory" type="fix" due-to="Ingo Feltes">
        BaseConfiguration does not close the first appender.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Add MessageFormatMessage and FormattedMessage.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-134" dev="ggregory" type="add">
        Use %red, %white, %blue, and so on in the console appender.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-133" dev="ggregory" type="add">
        Allow custom message creation via a message factory.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-132" dev="ggregory" type="fix">
        AbstractLogger.catching(Throwable) checks for DEBUG level but logs at ERROR level.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-129" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        RoutingAppender was only creating a single appender for the default Route.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-126" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Allow JMS appenders to recover if the queue or topic is unavailable.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-128" dev="rgoers" type="update">
        Add follow attribute to Console Appender.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-127" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        AbstractLogger methods were not passing Markers to the isEnabled methods.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Added Flume Appender samples.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-122" dev="rgoers" type="update">
        Add unit test to verify exceptions are thrown when the socket connection fails.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-125" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        JMSQueue and JMSTopic Appenders did not allow name to be specified.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-111" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Enhanced javadoc copyright statement.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-110" dev="rgoers" type="update">
        Renamed log4j12-api to log4j-1.2-api.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-120" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        TCPSocketManager would fail if the initial connection could not be established.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-119" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        A broken socket connection would cause the TCPSocketManager to continuously reconnect.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-123" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="Olivier Lamy">
        The example for ThreadContextMapFilter was incorrect.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-116" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        File renaming was using the wrong date value. Enhanced DefaultRolloverStrategy to store newest files in
        highest index as well as lowest.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-115" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        ThreadContext Map elements with null values are now ignored when constructing a Flume event and in the
        RFC5424 Layout.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-113" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        StructuredDataFilter createFilter was annotated with PluginAttr instead of PluginElement for the
        KeyValuePairs.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-114" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="Arkin Yetis">
        StructuredDataMessage was validating the length of the values in the event Map instead of the lengths
        of the keys.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="2.0-beta3" date="2012-11-11" description= "Bug fixes and enhancements">
      <action issue="LOG4J2-108" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Fix NullPointerException in ClassLoaderContextSelector when no class is returned from
        the SecurityManager.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-105" dev="rgoers" type="update">
        Add ability to customize the names of the Levels in the LevelPatternConverter.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-107" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        PatternParser was not properly handling adjacent nested options
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-95" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Add support for loading plugins inside the OSGi bundle.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-85" dev="rgoers" type="update">
        Add ThreadContext.push(String format, Object... args)
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-103" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="Das Archive">
        The LogEvent was wrapping a ThrowableProxy with another ThrowableProxy when deserializing.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="update">
        Created combined jar to combine API and Core contents for users who only want the Log4j implementation.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-104" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Convert LogManager binding to use "regular" java properties instead of XML properties to workaround a
        bug in Oracle's xmlparserv2 jar.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-28" dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Added PropertiesRewritePolicy and ability to define properties on a Logger.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-87" dev="rgoers" type="update">
        Build pdf of user's guide.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-29" dev="rgoers" type="update">
        Added font and fontSize parameters to HTMLLayout. Replace newlines in message with br tag.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-55" dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Added ability to configure from an InputSource.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-102" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="Emanuele Colombo">
        The Facility value was being improperly calculated.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-101" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="Emanuele Colombo">
        A NullPointerException would occur if no format value was passed to the SyslogAppender.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-99" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="Das Archive">
        MapRewritePolicy had an extra call to putAll that caused updates to behave like adds.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Avoid NPE when duplicate LoggerContextFactorys are present. Allow factories to specify a weight to allow
        real implementations to outrank test implementations. Provide a simple default LoggerContextFactory.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-97" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Added several missing classes and methods for Log4j 1.x compatibility.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-94" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="Denis Treskunov">
        Interpolator was not stripping Lookup key separator when trying to locate the default value for a variable.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Log4j 1.2 Category.forcedLog was wrapping the message with an ObjectMessage even if the parameter was an
        ObjectMessage.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="2.0-beta2" date="2012-10-07" description="Bug fixes and enhancements">
      <action dev="rgoers" type="update">
        Made ParameterizedMessage, StringFormattedMessage and ThreadDumpMessage immutable. LocalizedMessage is
        immutable except that it will be updated with the logger name when it is added to the LogEvent.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        DefaultConfiguration was not starting the Console Appender.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-35" dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Add interval and modulate options to TimeBasedTriggeringPolicy to allow more fine-grained control of
        when file rolling should occur.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-58" dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Add support for filtering packages from stack traces.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-84" dev="rgoers" type="add">
        If system property "disableThreadContextStack" is set pushes to the ThreadContext will be ignored. If
        system property "disableThreadContext" is set both puts and pushes will be ignored.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-83" dev="rgoers" type="add">
        If system property "disableThreadContextMap" is set puts to the ThreadContext will be ignored. If
        system property "disableThreadContext" is set both puts and pushes will be ignored.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Add support for ANSI colors by adding the highlight and style pattern converters. Fix pattern
        parsing to allow nested patterns.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-92" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Converted DynamicThresholdFilter to use KeyValuePair. Fixed bugs in the Map-based filters
        to allow declaration of multiple values for a key to match the documentation.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-88" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Many logging methods in AbstractLogger were set to an incorrect logging level. catching was
        using the THROWING marker and was set to debug instead of error.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Allow the status logging to be directed to stderr or to a file.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-91" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Log4j 1.2 adapter's Category class was missing 3 log methods.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-84" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        If the ThreadContext stack is empty the LogEvent will contain a null value to reduce the overhead of
        creating log events and in the size of the serialized object. Changed the ThreadContext stack to use
        a custom stack interface instead of java.util.Stack as that class is overly heavy. This change will
        cause an API incompatibility.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-83" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        If the ThreadContext map is empty the LogEvent will contain a null value to reduce the overhead of creating
        log events and in the size of the serialized object.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Add getFormats to MultiformatMessage and allow StructuredDataMessage to format as XML.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-90" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Add documentation on client vs server mode to performance page.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Move variable substitution from PatternLayout to appropriate converters to improve performance.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="2.0-beta1" date="2012-09-18" description="Bug fixes and enhancements">
      <action dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Added AsynchAppender.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J-81" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        PatternLayout was not honoring format modifiers.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Created web module to allow web applications to include the Log4j context listener in WEB-INF/lib even if
        Log4j is in the container's class path. Allow locating the LoggerContext to include the ClassLoader. Updated
        the Loader utility to always choose the child ClassLoader. Verified in Jboss 5 and Tomcat.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-82" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        MarkerFilter called MarkerManager.getMarker causing the Marker to be created during the processing of the
        configuration. This prevents the application from creating the Marker with any parents. MarkerWrapper in
        SLF4J-impl was getting a ClassCastException in instanceOf because the Marker isn't a MarkerWrapper.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-80" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="Oliver Lamy">
        Allow Log4j 2 to be used as the implementation with SLF4J and SLF4J's jcl-over-slf4j by adding filtering
        to the log method in SLF4JLogger.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-78" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        LogFactoryImpl.setAttribute in the Commons Logging bridge got a NullPointerException when passed a null value.
        It will now remove the attribute.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-77" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        RoutingAppender was calling the stop method for each of its referenced Appenders and was calling
        the stop method of the default Appender a second time. It will now only call the stop method of
        Appenders it creates.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-76" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        RewriteAppender was calling the stop method of the referenced appender causing the referenced appender's
        manager to have its use count decremented too many times.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-74" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Logger.error(Marker, Message, Throwable) was internally using Level.TRACE.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-75" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Enhanced Log4jContextListener to accept a configuration file location. Modified FileConfigurationMonitor
        to monitor files configured that way. Fixed other reconfiguration related bugs. Tested in JBoss and
        Tomcat.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-72" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        NullPointerException in RollingFileManager when filePattern does not cause the file to be compressed.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-71" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        FileRenameAction did not create the parent directories of the archive files causing the rollover to fail.
      </action>
      <action dev="rgoers" type="update">
        Update the versions of SLF4J and Logback.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="2.0-alpha2" date="2012-08-24" description="Bug fixes and minor enhancements">
      <action issue="LOG4J2-70" dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Add getLogger(Class) to LogManager.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-69" dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Allow Flume agents to be embedded into the Flume Appender.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-68" dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Add support for formatting using String.format().
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-67" dev="rgoers" type="add">
        Allow components besides core to create a PluginMap for faster plugin loading and not
        having to specify the plugin package in the configuration.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-64" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Fix compilation problems in Java 7.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-65" dev="rgoers" type="fix">
        Allow variable substitution on the configuration attributes and on the root log level.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="2.0-alpha1" date="2012-07-29" description="Rewrite of Log4j">
      <action issue="LOG4J2-60" dev="rgoers" type="add" due-to="Shane Kelly">
        Added ability to filter on the appender-ref by adding either a level or a filter.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-56" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="John Owen Atala">
        Level.toLevel would throw an IllegalArgumentException instead of returning the default value.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-51" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="John Vasileff">
        Remove LoggerContext support for custom logger factories. All Loggers returned
        by LoggerContext should be compatibile and of the same type.
      </action>
      <action issue="LOG4J2-50" dev="rgoers" type="fix" due-to="John Vasileff">
        Make sure all application facing log methods use their own FQCN. This patch
        resolves a unit test failure for the %C pattern when using the Category logger.
      </action>
    </release>
  </body>
</document>
