<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

         http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->

<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Log4j 2 Guide</title>
        <author email="rgoers@apache.org">Ralph Goers</author>
        <author email="ggregory@apache.org">Gary Gregory</author>
        <author email="sdeboy@apache.org">Scott Deboy</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Apache Log4j 2">

          <p>
            Apache Log4j 2 is an upgrade to Log4j that provides significant improvements over its predecessor, Log4j
            1.x, and provides many of the improvements available in Logback while fixing some inherent problems in
            Logback's architecture.
          </p>

          <p>Some of the features and improvements in Log4j 2 are:</p>

          <dl>
            <dt>API Separation</dt>
            <dd>
              The API for Log4j is separate from the implementation making it clear for application developers
              which classes and methods they can use while ensuring forward compatibility. This allows the
              Log4j team to improve the implementation safely and in a compatible manner.
            </dd>
            <dt>Improved Performance</dt>
            <dd>
              Log4j 2 contains next-generation lock-free Asynchronous Loggers based
              on the LMAX Disruptor library. In multi-threaded scenarios
              Asynchronous Loggers have 18 times higher throughput and
              orders of magnitude lower latency than Log4j 1.x and Logback.
              See <a href="manual/async.html#Performance">Asynchronous Logging Performance</a>
              for details.
              Otherwise, Log4j 2 significantly outperforms Log4j 1.x, Logback and java.util.logging,
              especially in multi-threaded applications.
              See <a href="performance.html">Performance</a> for more information.
            </dd>
            <dt>Support for multiple APIs</dt>
            <dd>
              While the Log4j 2 API will provide the best performance, Log4j 2 provides support for the
              Log4j 1.2, SLF4J, Commons Logging and java.util.logging (JUL) APIs.
            </dd>
            <dt>Avoid lock-in</dt>
            <dd>
              Applications coded to the Log4j 2 API always have the option to use any SLF4J-compliant
              library as their logger implementation with the log4j-to-slf4j adapter.
            </dd>
            <dt>Automatic Reloading of Configurations</dt>
            <dd>
              Like Logback, Log4j 2 can automatically reload its configuration upon modification. Unlike Logback,
              it will do so without losing log events while reconfiguration is taking place.
            </dd>
            <dt>Advanced Filtering</dt>
            <dd>
              Like Logback, Log4j 2 supports filtering based on context data, markers, regular expressions,
              and other components in the Log event. Filtering can be specified to apply to all events
              before being passed to Loggers or as they pass through Appenders. In addition, filters can also
              be associated with Loggers. Unlike Logback, you can use a common Filter class in any of these
              circumstances.
            </dd>
            <dt>Plugin Architecture</dt>
            <dd>
              Log4j uses the plugin pattern to configure components. As such, you do not need to write code
              to create and configure an Appender, Layout, Pattern Converter, and so on. Log4j automatically
              recognizes plugins and uses them when a configuration references them.
            </dd>
            <dt>Property Support</dt>
            <dd>
              You can reference properties in a configuration, Log4j will directly replace them, or Log4j will
              pass them to an underlying component that will dynamically resolve them. Properties come from values
              defined in the configuration file, system properties, environment variables, the ThreadContext
              Map, and data present in the event. Users can further customize the property providers by
              adding their own <a href="manual/lookups.html">Lookup</a> Plugin.
            </dd>
            <dt>Java 8 Lambda Support</dt>
            <dd>
              Previously, if a log message was expensive to construct, you would often explicitly check if the
              requested log level is enabled before constructing the message.
              Client code running on Java 8 can benefit from Log4j's <a href="manual/api.html#LambdaSupport">lambda
              support</a>. Since Log4j will not evaluate a lambda
              expression if the requested log level is not enabled, the same effect can be achieved with less code.
            </dd>
            <dt>Custom Log Levels</dt>
            <dd>
              In Log4j 2, <a href="manual/customloglevels.html">custom log levels</a> can easily be defined in code
              or in configuration. No subclassing is required.
            </dd>
            <dt>Garbage-free</dt>
            <dd>
              During steady state logging, Log4j 2 is <a href="manual/garbagefree.html">garbage-free</a>
              in stand-alone applications, and low garbage in web applications.
              This reduces pressure on the garbage collector and can give better response time performance.
            </dd>
          </dl>

          <subsection name="Documentation">
            <p>
              The Log4j 2 User's Guide is available on this <a href="manual/index.html">site</a> or as a downloadable
              <a href="log4j-users-guide.pdf">PDF</a>.
            </p>
          </subsection>

          <subsection name="Requirements">
             <p>
               Log4j 2.4 and greater requires Java 7, versions 2.0-alpha1 to 2.3 required Java 6.
               Some features require optional dependencies; the documentation for these features specifies the
               dependencies.
            </p>
          </subsection>

          <subsection name="News">
            <p>
              Log4j 2 is now available for production. The API for Log4j 2 is not compatible with Log4j 1.x, however an adapter
              is available to allow applications to continue to use the Log4j 1.x API. Adapters are also available for
              Apache Commons Logging and SLF4J.
            </p>
          </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>

