<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

         http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->

<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Performance</title>
    <author email="rgoers@apache.org">Ralph Goers</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Performance">
      <p>One of the often-cited arguments against logging is its
        computational cost. This is a legitimate concern as even moderately
        sized applications can generate thousands of log requests. Much
        effort was spent measuring and tweaking logging performance. Log4j
        claims to be fast and flexible: speed first, flexibility second.
      </p>
      <p>The user should be aware of the following performance issues.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <h3>Logging performance when logging is turned off.</h3>
          <p>When logging is turned off entirely or just for a set of Levels, the cost of a log request consists of
            two method invocations plus an integer comparison. On a 2.53 GHz Intel Core 2 Duo MacBook Pro
            calling isDebugEnabled 10 million times produces an average result in nanoseconds of:</p>
            <pre>
            Log4j: 4
            Logback: 5
            Log4j 2: 3
            </pre>
          <p>
            The numbers above will vary slightly from run to run so the only conclusion that should be
            drawn is that all 3 frameworks perform similarly on this task.
          </p>
          <p>However, The method invocation involves the "hidden" cost of parameter construction.
          </p>
          <p>For example,
          </p>
            <pre>
              logger.debug("Entry number: " + i + " is " + String.valueOf(entry[i]));
            </pre>
          <p>
            incurs the cost of constructing the message parameter, i.e. converting both integer
            <code>i</code> and <code>entry[i]</code> to a String, and concatenating intermediate strings,
            regardless of whether the message will be logged or not.

            This cost of parameter construction can be quite high and it
            depends on the size of the parameters involved.

            A comparison run on the same hardware as above yields:
          </p>
            <pre>
            Log4j: 188
            Logback: 183
            Log4j 2: 188
            </pre>
          <p>
            Again, no conclusion should be drawn regarding relative differences between the frameworks on
            this task, but it should be obvious that it is considerably more expensive than simply testing
            the level.
          </p>
          <p>
            The best approach to avoid the cost of parameter construction is to use Log4j 2's formatting
            capabilities. For example, instead of the above write:
          </p>
            <pre>
            logger.debug("Entry number: {} is {}", i, entry[i]);
            </pre>
          <p>
            Using this approach, a comparison run again on the same hardware produces:
          </p>
            <pre>
            Log4j: Not supported
            Logback: 9
            Log4j 2: 4
            </pre>
          <p>
            These results show that the difference in performance between the call to isDebugEnabled and
            logger.debug is barely discernible.
          </p>
          <p>In some circumstances one of the parameters to logger.debug will be a costly method call that
            should be avoided if debugging is disabled. In those cases write:
          </p>
            <pre>
            if(logger.isDebugEnabled() {
                logger.debug("Entry number: " + i + " is " + entry[i].toString());
            }
            </pre>
          <p>This will not incur the cost of whatever the toString() method needs to do if debugging is disabled.
            On the other hand, if the logger is enabled for the debug level, it will incur twice the cost of
            evaluating whether the logger is enabled or not: once
            in <code>isDebugEnabled</code> and once in <code>debug</code>. This is an insignificant
            overhead because evaluating a logger takes about 1% of the time it takes to actually log.
          </p>
          <p>Certain users resort to pre-processing or compile-time
            techniques to compile out all log statements. This leads to perfect
            performance efficiency with respect to logging. However, since the
            resulting application binary does not contain any log statements,
            logging cannot be turned on for that binary. This seems to be
            a disproportionate price to pay in exchange for a small performance
            gain.
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <h3>The performance of deciding whether to log or not to log when logging is turned on.</h3>
          <p>
            Unlike Log4j, Log4j 2 Loggers don't "walk a hierarchy". Loggers point directly to the
            Logger configuration that best matches the Logger's name. This incurs extra overhead when the Logger
            is first created but reduces the overhead every time the Logger is used.
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <h3>Actually outputting log messages</h3>
          <p>This is the cost of formatting the log output and sending it to its target destination. Here again,
            a serious effort was made to make layouts (formatters) perform as quickly as possible. The same
            is true for appenders. One of the fundamental tenets of Log4j 2 is to use immutable objects whenever
            possible and to lock at the lowest granularity possible. However, the cost of actually formatting and
            delivering log events will never be insignificant. For example, the results of writing to a simple log
            file using the same format using Log4j, Logback and Log4j 2 are:
          </p>
          <pre>
              Log4j: 1651
              Logback: 1419
              Log4j 2.0: 1542
          </pre>
          <p>
            As with many of the other results on this page the differences between the frameworks above should be
            considered insignificant. The values will change somewhat on each execution and changing the order the
            frameworks are tested or adding calls to System.gc() between the tests can cause a variation in the
            reported times. However, these results show that actually writing out the events can be at least 1000
            times more expensive than when they are disabled, so it is always recommended to take advantage of
            Log4j 2's fine-grained filtering capabilities.
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <h3>Advanced Filtering</h3>
          <p>
            Both Logback and Log4j 2 support advanced filtering. Logback calls them TurboFilters while
            Log4j 2 has a single Filter object. Advanced filtering provides the capability to filter
            LogEvents using more than just the Level before the events are passed to Appenders.
            However, this flexibility does come with some cost. Since multi-threading can also have an impact on the
            performance of advanced filtering, the table below shows the difference in performance in two different
            sets of context-wide filters running on the same hardware as the previous tests using
            various numbers of threads.
          </p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Test</th>
              <th>1 thread</th>
              <th>2 threads</th>
              <th>5 threads</th>
              <th>10 threads</th>
              <th>20 threads</th>
              <th>50 threads</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Logback MDCFilter</td>
              <td>37</td>
              <td>50</td>
              <td>145</td>
              <td>316</td>
              <td>606</td>
              <td>1670</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Log4j 2 ThreadContextMapFilter</td>
              <td>30</td>
              <td>35</td>
              <td>85</td>
              <td>165</td>
              <td>341</td>
              <td>864</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Logback MarkerFilter</td>
              <td>17</td>
              <td>24</td>
              <td>59</td>
              <td>115</td>
              <td>234</td>
              <td>547</td>
            </tr>
             <tr>
              <td>Log4j 2 MarkerFilter</td>
              <td>4</td>
              <td>5</td>
              <td>7</td>
              <td>20</td>
              <td>35</td>
              <td>92</td>
            </tr>
          </table>
        </li>
        <li>
          <h3>Client vs Server</h3>
          <p>
            Java supports a "client" and a "server" mode of operation. By default, applications that are
            run in Java 5 on machines with 2 CPUs or more and 2GB of memory or more on operating systems
            other than Windows or are run in a 64-bit JVM are automatically configured to run in "server" mode.
            Testing has shown that Log4j 2 benefits greatly from running in server mode and user's are
            strongly encouraged to configure their applications to run in server mode when using Log4j 2.
          </p>
        </li>
		<li>
		<h3>Asynchronous Logging Performance Improvements</h3>
		<p>
		Log4j 2 offers Asynchronous Loggers for high throughput and low latency logging.
		Asynchronous Loggers are implemented using the
		<a href="http://lmax-exchange.github.com/disruptor/">LMAX Disruptor</a>
		inter-thread messaging library instead of the ArrayBlockingQueue used by Asynchronous Appenders.
		</p><p>
		Asynchronous Appenders already offered about 5 - 10 times more throughput than
		synchronous loggers, but this advantage remained more or less constant
		when more threads are logging. That is, if you double the number of threads
		that are logging you would expect your total throughput to increase, but
		this is not the case: the throughput per thread is roughly halved so your
		total throughput remains more or less the same.
		(Note that this happens even if the appender queue size is large enough to hold
		all messages logged during the test, so this is not caused by disk I/O.)
		</p><p>
		Asynchronous Loggers have significantly higher throughput than the legacy Asynchronous Appenders,
		especially in multi-threaded scenarios. In one test with 64 threads,
		Asynchronous Loggers were 12 times faster than the fastest Asynchronous Appender,
		and 68 times faster than the fastest synchronous logger.
		In addition to throughput, Asynchronous Loggers have attractive latency characteristics.
		Not only is average latency lower compared to Asynchronous Appenders,
		but when increasing the number of application threads that do logging,
		worst-case latency remained almost constant (10 - 20 microseconds)
		where Asynchronous Appenders start experiencing worst-case
		latency spikes in the 100 millisecond range, a difference of four orders of magnitude.
		See <a href="manual/async.html#Performance">Asynchronous Logging Performance</a> for details.
		</p>
		</li>
      </ol>
      <p>
        The performance results above were all derived from running the DebugDisabledPerformanceComparison,
        FilterPerformanceComparison, and PerformanceComparison junit tests which can be found in the
        Log4j 2 unit test source directory.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
